Guide to the Bay Area Research Collective - Underground Newspapers Collection, 1969-1956 LAC0009
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Bay Area Research Collective - Underground Newspapers Collection
1969-1986
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
LAC0009
8.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains material amassed by a member of the Bay Area Research Collective (BARC), a radical left-wing publishing collective and distributor active during the 1970s. Included are newspapers and subject files dating from 1969-1986.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains material amassed by a member of the Bay Area Research Collective (BARC), a radical left-wing publishing collective and distributor active during the 1970s. According to its journal "Dragon," the driving force behind the work of the BARC was that "aboveground, underground, and locked down are three facets of the same struggle," and that their purpose was to "try to break down the barriers among the three through support and criticism, at all times trying to build unity."
Split into two series, the collection is comprised mostly of underground newspapers, mainstream newspaper clippings and other material produced by or related to radical left-wing and revolutionary groups of the post-1960s American and international Left. As a whole the materials document a large swath of organizations, movements and issues of the time, from American revolutionary communist and Black Power groups to the national liberation and anti-imperialist movements of Latin America and Southeast Asia. Produced between the years of 1969 and 1986, there is throughout the collection an emphasis on the theory and practice of armed struggle, emergent Black Power and feminist politics, and the need for anti-imperialist/internationalist solidarity, all indicative of the context out of which the materials come.
Most of the materials in Series 1, Newspapers, are dedicated to local community and movement news, but also included are college campus newspapers, including the University of California at Berkeley's Daily Californian, and papers produced by specific organizations, including Palante, published by the Young Lords Party, Sun/Dance, published by the White Panter Party, and the SCAR'd Times, published by the Statewide Correctional Alliance for Reform, a radical prisoner's rights organization. There are also specific issue journals dealing with women's liberation, black liberation, drug use issues and Native peoples' issues.
The materials in Series 2, Subject Files, are arranged into folders by the organization which produced them, the topic of the materials included or the title of publication. The majority of the materials are from various radical and revolutionary left-wing organizations, including among many others the Black Panther Party, the Black Liberation Army, the Weather Underground Organization, the Youth International Party, and the Symbionese Liberation Army. These folders mostly contain newspaper clippings, but also communiques, correspondence and radical publications. The various folders arranged by topic cover labor issues, women's issues, terrorism, the Vietnam War, the murder of Popeye Jackson, the ecology movement, among many other subjects, and also generally contain newspaper clippings and other publications.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series. Series 1, Newspapers, contains underground radical left-wing newspapers and publications dating from 1970-1986. Series 2, Subject Files, contains a variety of materials arranged into folders documenting revolutionary New Left and post-New Left organizations and issues, dating from 1969-1982.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift, 2012 [2012.048].
Underground literature -- Soviet Union; Radicals
- Newspapers, 1970-1986; Series 1; 3.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains underground newspapers and newsletters published by New Left and post-New Left radical left-wing organizations and publishing collectives between 1970 and 1986. With the exception of two papers, all were produced in the United States. Most of the papers included are dedicated to basic community and movement news, but there are also college campus newspapers, including the University of California at Berkeley's Daily Californian, as well as specific issue journals dealing with women's liberation, black liberation, drug use issues and Native peoples' issues. Of particular note are those newspapers published by specific organizations. These include Palante, published by the Young Lords Party, Sun/Dance, published by the White Panter Party, and the SCAR'd Times, published by the Statewide Correctional Alliance for Reform, a radical prisoner's rights organization.
  - Akwesasne Notes, 1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Published by the Mohawk Nation via Roosevelt Town, NY
  - Anarchist Black Dragon - Washington State Penitentiary, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ann Arbor Argus, 1971 April - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ann Arbor Sun - Weekly Community News Service, 1971 June - December; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Published by the Rainbow People's Party
  - Ann Arbor Sun - Weekly Community News Service, 1972 January - March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Augur, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Published in Eugene, OR
  - Bar None, 1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Published in W. Somerville, MA
  - Berkeley Barb, 1975 April; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Berkeley Tribe, 1971 February; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Published by The Red Mountain Tribe, Inc.
  - Challenge! Quad-Cities Community News Service, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Published in Davenport, IA
  - The Children's Advocate of Berkeley, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Published by Berkeley Children's Services
  - Community Services United, 1978 February - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Published in Berkeley, CA
  - Community Services United, 1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Daily Californian, 1986 January 21; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Published at the University of California at Berkeley
  - The East Bay Voice - An Opposition Newsmonthly, 1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Published by the East Bay chapter of the New American Movement
  - Express - The East Bay's Free Weekly, 1978 October; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Freedom Reader, 1972 January - April; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Published in Flint, MI
  - Gathering Place, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Published in Honolulu, HI
  - Grassroots - Berkeley's Community Newspaper, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hawaiian Ethos, 1971 March; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hundred Flowers - Community News and Info., 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Published in Minneapolis, MN
  - Hundred Flowers - A Journal of Revolutionary Art and Politics, 1977 April; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Joint Issue, 1972; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Published in Lansing, MI
  - Juche, 1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Published in Cambridge, MA
  - The Kalamazoo Patriot, 1971; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Published in Kalamazoo, MI
  - The Liberated Guardian, 1971 October 14; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    A National Liberated Publication. Published in New York, NY.
  - Madness Network News, 1975 July; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Majority Report - The Women's Newspaper, 1973-1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Published in New York, NY
  - Michigan Free Press, 1977 January - February; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Michigan Free Press, 1977 February; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Michigan Free Press, 1977 May-June; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Michigan Free Press, 1977 July; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Michigan Free Press, 1977 October; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Michigan Free Press, 1977 November; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Michigan Free Press, Clippings on International Affairs, 1975; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Michigan Free Press, Clippings on International Affairs, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Mole, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Published in Boston, MA
  - New Morning, 1973 September; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Published in Ann Arbor, MI
  - NOLA Express, 1972 March; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Published in New Orleans, LA
  - Northwest Passage, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Published in Bellingham, WA
  - Off Our Backs - A Women's News Journal, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Published in Washington, DC
  - Off Our Backs - A Women's News Journal, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Off Our Backs - A Women's News Journal, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Old Mole, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Outlaw, 1972 January; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Published in St. Louis, MO
  - Overthrow, 1984-1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    A Yippie publication. Published in New York, NY.
  - Paine, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Published in Bangor, ME
  - Palante, 1972; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Published by the Young Lords Party
  - People's Forum, 1977; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Published by People's Temple of the Disciples of Christ in San Francisco, CA
  - Plain Dealer, 1970; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Published in Philadelphia, PA
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1974 March-December; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1975 January-July; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1975 August - 1976 January; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1976 February - September; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1976 October - 1977 May; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1977 August - 1978 July; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Plexus - Bay Area Women's Newspaper, 1978 August - November; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Portland Scribe, 1972 March - April; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rainbow News Service, 1971 December 4; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Published by the Rainbow People's Party in Ann Arbor, MI
  - Rat, 1970 October; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Recon, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Resurrection - People's News Service, 1970 June - 1971 January; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Published by the John Brown Party in Tuscon, AZ
  - Resurrection - People's News Service, 1971 March-June; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Root - A Grand Rapids People's Paper, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - SCAR'd Times, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Published by the Statewide Correctional Alliance for Reform (SCAR) in Portland, ME
  - The Second Coming, 1971; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Published in Ypsilanti, MI
  - Seize the Time, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Published in San Jose, CA
  - Shelter, 1971; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Published in Kansas City, MO
  - Sister - West Coast Feminist Newspaper, 1975 July; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Published in Venice, CA
  - Sun/Dance - White Panther Information Services, 1970 October; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sunfighter, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Published in Seattle, WA
  - Take One, 1976 August; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Published in Montreal, Quebec
  - Take Over, 1977-1979; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Published in Madison, WI
  - Vortex, 1971; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Published in Lawrence, KA
  - Westport Trucker, 1971; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Women's Press, 1975 June; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Zero - An Anarchist/Anarca-feminist Monthly, 1977 June - 1978 August; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Published in London, England
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1970s; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Subject Files, 1969-1982; Series 2; 5 Linear Feet
  This series is comprised of folders containing a variety of materials from revoultionary left-wing organizations and related issues dating from 1969-1982. The materials are arranged into folders by the organization which produced them, the topic of the materials included or the title of publication. The majority of the materials are from various radical left-wing organizations of the New Left and post New-Left period, including the Black Panther Party, the Black Liberation Army, the Weather Underground Organization, the Youth International Party, the George Jackson Brigade, the Symbionese Liberation Army, the New World Liberation Front and the United Prisoners' Union. These folders mostly contain newspaper clippings, but also communiques, correspondence and radical publications (including the Weather Underground Organization's "Prairie Fire" paper and the New World Liberation Front's "Urban Guerrilla" journal). The various folders arranged by topic cover labor issues, women's issues, terrorism, the Vietnam War, the murder of Popeye Jackson, the Jonestown mass suicide and the ecology movement, among many other subjects, and also generally contain newspaper clippings and other publications.
  - Africa Research Group, 1970-1972; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alternative Press, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Anarchist Party of Canada, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Anti-War Issues, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bay Area Research Collective, 1975-1978; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bay Area Women Against Rape, 1978; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Berkeley, 1969-1971; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Berkeley Tribe - Correspondence, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - The Black Guerrilla Family - Correspondence, 1974; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Black Liberation Army [1/2], 1975-1981; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Black Liberation Army [2/2], 1975-1981; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Black Panther Party, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Children's Liberation, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Communist Party, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Counter-Terrorist Task Force, 1976; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Dragon" - Bay Area Research Collective Journal, 1975 August; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Ecology Movement, 1969-1971; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Faye Stender, 1981; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Fred Hampton Unit, 1976; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Free People's Liberation Army, 1976; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Le Front de Liberation du Quebec (Quebec Liberation Front), 1970-1976; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Fuerzas Armadas de Liberacion Nacional Puertorriquena (Armed Forces of Puerto Rican National Liberation), 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - George Jackson Brigade [1/3], 1976-1978; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - George Jackson Brigade [2/3], 1976-1978; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - George Jackson Brigade [3/3], 1976-1978; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - George Jackson Brigade - Correspondence, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - George Jackson Brigade - Grand Jury [1/2], 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - George Jackson Brigade - Grand Jury [2/2], 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - George Jackson Brigade - Newspaper Clippings, 1976; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Grand Juries, 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Image Clippings, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Japan, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - July 4th Coalition, 1976; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Korea, 1970; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Labor Issues [1/2], 1969-1971; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Labor Issues [2/2], 1969-1971; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Laos, 1971; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Latin America, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Martin Sostre, 1973-1975; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Mass Intermediate Socialist Organization, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Mexico, 1971; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Native American Issues, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - New Dawn Party [1/3], 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - New Dawn Party [2/3], 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - New Dawn Party [3/3], 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - New World Liberation Front [1/4], 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - New World Liberation Front [2/4], 1974-1977; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - New World Liberation Front [3/4], 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - New World Liberation Front [4/4], 1972-1977; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - New World Liberation Front - Health Campaign, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Northern Ireland, 1971-1972; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Oakland, 1971-1973; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Orphans of Amerika, 1975; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Peoples Temple/Jonestown Mass-Suicide Clippings, 1978; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - The Phillipines, 1971; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Poetry, 1976; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Police, 1971; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Popeye Jackson Murder, 1975; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Prison Activism, 1977-1981; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Puerto Rico, 1976-1979; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Recipes, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - The Red Guerrilla Family, 1976; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Richard Picariello, 1976-1978; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Sam Melville - Jonathon Jackson Unit, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - San Diego Convention Coalition, 1972; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Seattle, 1971; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [1/9], 1972-1976; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [2/9], 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [3/9], 1976; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [4/9], 1976; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [5/9], 1974-1979; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [6/9], 1975; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [7/9], 1975; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [8/9], 1975-1978; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Clippings [9/9], 1975-1979; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Symbionese Liberation Army - Correspondence, 1974-1980; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Technology and Media, 1969-1975; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Terrorism, 1975-1979; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - United Prisoners' Union, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - The Urban Guerrilla Newsletter, 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam [1/2], 1969-1974; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Vietnam [2/3], 1969-1975; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam [3/3], 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Weather Underground Organizaton - Clippings, 1974-1981; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Weather Underground Organization - Communiques, 1970-1976; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Weather Underground Organization - "Osawatomie", 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Weather Underground Organization - "Prairie Fire" Paper, 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Weather Underground Organization - Self-Criticism, 1976; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Weather Underground Organization - Split, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - White Panther Party, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Women's Issues, 1974-1982; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Youth International Party, 1970s; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Youth Issues, 1969-1971; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1980s; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 5)